Beyond Journey's End
え～っとね　長距離魔法は➡
Long-range magic is a combination of
three key factors essential to mages.
魔法使いに必須な
３つの要素の合わせ技で➡
構成されているんだけど…。
１つは魔力の量と
それを打ち出す力の強さ。
There's the amount of mana,
the strength with which it's fired, and the
level of control the mage has over it.
そして　コントロールする力。
ここまでは知ってるよね？
はい。
You know that much, don't you?
Yes.
さっきは途中で
魔法が離散してしまったね。
Earlier, your magic dissipated
before it reached its target.
魔力の量と打ち出す力が
足りないことを示している。
That's a sign that your mana
and firing strength are lacking.
それは　一朝一夕で
どうにかなることじゃ　ない。
It's not something you can fix overnight.
才能にかかわらず➡
Regardless of your talent,
it'll take years to master.
何年もかけていかなければ
いけないよ。
けど　魔力をコントロールする力は
とても高いみたいだね。
However, your level of control
over the magic is very high.
みんな
そこで　てこずるんだけど➡
That's what most people
tend to have trouble with.
その心配は　なさそうだし➡
But you've got no problems there,
気長に取り組むことだね。
so just be patient with yourself.
はい…。
Okay.
（足音）
フェルンの修行は順調ですか？
Is Fern's training coming along smoothly?
常人なら１０年かかる道を
４年で越えた。
In just four years, she's learned more
than most people do in ten.
あの子は打ち込み過ぎだ
あまりいいことじゃ　ない。
She's studying too hard.
It's not a good thing.
最近　ずっと
森に　こもりきりですからね。
She's been spending all her
time in the woods lately.
それだけ魔法が好きなのでしょう。
She must really love magic.
それでも　一人前になるのは
まだ先のことだ。
But she's still a long way
from becoming a proper mage.
魔導書の解読のほうが
早く終わるよ。
I'll finish deciphering the
grimoire before she does.
そうですか。
I see.
ねぇ　ハイター。
Say, Heiter.
この魔導書だけど　多分…。
This grimoire probably...
（倒れた音）
ハイター？
Heiter?
そんな顔をしないでください。
Don't look at me like that.
今まで　まともに動けていたほうが
奇跡だったのです。
If anything, it's a miracle
I've been mobile until now.
魔導書の解読　急ぐよ。
I'll try to decipher the grimoire quickly.
お願いします。
I'd appreciate that.
フェルン　修行は中止だ。
Fern, put your training on hold.
ハイターが倒れた
そばにいてやってくれ。
Heiter collapsed.
I need you to stay with him.
まだ　一番岩を
打ち抜けておりません。
But I still haven't hit the rock.
それは　いずれ必ずできることだ。
You'll do it eventually. Right now—
今は…。
いずれではダメなのです！
Eventually isn't good enough.
いずれでは…➡
Mr. Heiter will die before then.
ハイター様が死んでしまう。
私は　あの方に命を救われました。
He saved my life.
｟今　死ぬのは
もったいないと思いますよ｠
It'd be a waste for you to die now.
｟もったいない？｠
A waste?
｟もう随分前になりますか…｠
A long time ago, I lost an old friend.
｟古くからの友人を
亡くしましてね｠
｟私とは違って
ひたすらに真っすぐで➡
Unlike me, he was straight as an arrow,
困っている人を決して
見捨てないような人間でした｠
and he never abandoned
anyone who was in need.
｟私ではなく
彼が生き残っていれば➡
If he'd survived instead of me,
he would've saved a lot of people.
多くの者を救えたはずです｠
｟私は彼とは違うので➡
Since I'm not like him, I planned to
live out the rest of my days quietly,
おとなしく余生を過ごそうと
思っていたのですが➡
ある時
ふと気が付いてしまいまして｠
but one day, I suddenly realized something.
｟私が　このまま死んだら➡
If I died without doing anything,
彼から学んだ
勇気や意志や友情や➡
all the courage, strength of will,
and friendship I learned from him—
大切な思い出まで➡
even all my precious memories—
would vanish from this world.
この世から　なくなって
しまうのではないかと｠
｟あなたの中にも
大切な思い出があるとすれば➡
If you have precious memories
inside yourself as well,
死ぬのは
もったいないと思います｠
then I think it'd be a waste for you to die.
ハイター様は　ずっと➡
Mr. Heiter has always feared
dying and leaving me alone.
私を置いて死ぬことを
危惧しておりました。
あの方は正しいことをしたのです。
He did the right thing.
救ったことを後悔してほしくない。
I don't want him to regret saving me.
魔法使いでも何でもいい。
I don't care if it's as a mage
or whatever else—
１人で生きていくすべを
身に付けることが➡
learning some kind of skill to support
myself is my way of repaying him.
私の恩返しなのです。
救ってよかったと
もう大丈夫だと➡
I want him to be glad he saved me
and to know I'll be fine.
そう思ってほしいのです。
私が教えたことは
全部　覚えているよね。
You remember everything
I've taught you, don't you?
はい。
Yes.
じゃあ　好きにすればいい。
Then do as you like.
う…。
死者の蘇生も　不死の魔法も
書かれていなかったよ。
It didn't contain any spells for bringing
back the dead or granting immortality.
そうですか。
知っていたの？
I see.
Did you know that already?
死への恐怖は
計り知れないものです。
The fear of death is immeasurable.
そんなものがあるなら➡
If such spells existed,
Ewig would've cast them on himself.
エーヴィヒ自身が
使っていたでしょう。
じゃあ　なぜ…。
Then why?
フェルンは　どうなりましたか？
How is Fern?
まだ粗いところはあるけど➡
She has room for improvement in some areas,
一人前といっても
遜色のないレベルだよ。
but it wouldn't be wrong
to call her a proper mage.
そうですか　間に合いましたか。
ん？
I see. Then she made it in time.
もう足手まといではありませんね
フリーレン。
Now she won't get in your way, Frieren.
あ…。
｟あなたの旅に
連れていってくれませんか？｠
Will you bring her with you on your travels?
｟ごめん　ハイター
それだけはできない｠
I'm sorry, Heiter.
That's the one thing I can't do.
｟足手まといになるから｠
She'd only get in my way.
謀ったな　ハイター。
ハッハッハ。
You tricked me, Heiter.
解読の手間賃は　机の引き出しに。
Your payment for deciphering
the grimoire is in the desk drawer.
今夜には　ここを発ってください。
Please leave this place tonight.
何のつもり？
Why?
見ての通り
私は　もう長くはありません。
As you can see, I don't have much longer.
私は　あの子に　これ以上➡
I don't want her to experience
losing anyone else.
誰かを失うような経験を
させたくないのです。
フリーレン
フェルンを頼みましたよ。
Frieren, please look after Fern.
また格好をつけるのか　ハイター。
Are you trying to put on
a brave face again, Heiter?
フェルンは　とっくに
別れの準備はできている。
Fern has been ready to say goodbye
to you for some time now.
お前が死ぬまでに
やるべきことは➡
What you need to do before your death
あの子に
しっかりと別れを告げて➡
is give her a proper farewell
なるべく　たくさんの思い出を
つくってやることだ…。
and make as many memories as you can.
フリーレン➡
Frieren, you really are a kind girl.
あなたは　やはり優しい子です。
ねぇ　何でフェルンを救ったの？
Why did you save Fern?
勇者ヒンメルなら　そうしました。
It's what Himmel the Hero would've done.
（フリーレンの声）　そうだね。
You're right.
じゃあ　私も　そうするとするかな。
Then maybe I'll do the same.
（鐘の音）
（コルクを抜く音）
ありがとうございました。
Thank you.
おかげで　ハイター様に
恩を返すことができました。
Because of you, I was able to
repay my debt to Mr. Heiter.
私はただ　してやられただけだよ。
He just tricked me, is all.
この生臭坊主に。
This corrupt priest.
じゃあ　行こうか。
Shall we go, then?
Episode 2: It Didn't Have to Be Magic...
26 years after the death of Himmel the Hero,
in the Turk region located in the central lands
もういいよ　フェルン。
That's enough, Fern.
終わりだ。
We're finished.
（ドアの開閉音）
おかげで助かりました。
Thank you for your help.
こちらは約束の報酬です。
Here's your reward.
地味な仕事ばかりでございますね。
We've been doing such simple work.
冒険者なんて　こんなものだよ。
That's how adventuring goes.
報酬は何だったのですか？
民間魔法。
What were we paid in?
温かいお茶が出てくる魔法だって。
Folk magic. It's a spell
that produces warm tea.
後で実験しよう。
We'll try it out later.
（フェルンの声）　この前は銅像のサビを
キレイに取る魔法。
The other day we learned a spell
for removing rust from bronze statues.
それまた前は　甘いブドウを➡
Before that, we learned a spell
for turning sweet grapes into sour ones.
酸っぱいブドウに変える魔法。
｟酸っぱい…｠
How is it?
Sour.
変な魔法ばかり集めていますね。
You keep collecting the strangest spells.
趣味だからね。
It's my hobby, after all.
フリーレン様は
本当に魔法がお好きなのですね。
Ms. Frieren, you really do love magic.
ほどほどだよ　フェルンと同じで。
Only somewhat, like you.
少し違うような気がします。
I feel like we're a little different.
同じだよ。
We're the same.
（薬草家）　本当に頼み事を
聞いてもらってもいいのかしら？
Will you really do something for me?
私は薬草家だから➡
Since I'm an herbalist,
I don't have any spells to teach you.
教えられそうな魔法は
ないのだけれども…。
構わないよ。
That's fine. Just learning about
the local flora is helpful enough.
この地方の植生を
教えてくれるだけでも助かるから。
ここよ。
This is it.
勇者ヒンメル様の像ですか。
It's a statue of Himmel the Hero.
ひどい　ありさまでしょう？
It's in terrible shape, isn't it?
（薬草家）　年寄り１人では
もう　どうしようもなくてね。
It's too much for one old woman to handle.
村の人たちは
もう関心がないのよ。
And the villagers don't care anymore.
｟人々の悲鳴｠
｟逃げろ！｠
｟あぁ～！｠
Run!
｟大きな足音｠
｟うなり声｠
｟あっ　あぁ…｠
｟あぁ！｠
｟切りつける音｠
｟魔物が倒れた音｠
（薬草家の声）　ヒンメル様は
村が魔物に襲われた時➡
When the village was attacked by a monster,
必死に戦ってくれたのに…。
Mr. Himmel fought valiantly to defend us.
こんな仕打ちは
あまりにも　かわいそうだわ。
It saddens me to see him treated like this.
いや　自業自得だね。
No, it's what he deserves.
It's Himmel's fault for wanting to show off.
目立ちたがり屋のヒンメルが悪い。
村人が像を建てるって言った時に
断っていれば　よかったんだ。
When the villagers offered to make a statue
of him, he should have just declined.
（ヒンメル）｟大丈夫？　このポーズ
イケメン過ぎない？｠
Is this okay?
This pose isn't too handsome, is it?
（フリーレンの声）
ポーズに１８時間　悩んで
職人さん　ブチギレさせるし。
Just hurry up and pick something.
He drove the sculptor mad
by spending 18 hours choosing a pose.
I'm hungry.
結局
バカみたいに無難なポーズに➡
In the end, they settled on
a ridiculously plain one.
落ち着いたんだよね。
不思議なこと言うのね。
What a strange story.
そういえば　勇者様ご一行には
エルフの魔法使いがいたわね。
Come to think of it, there was an
elven mage in the hero's party.
じゃあ　片付けようか。
Shall we get this cleaned up?
（鳥の鳴き声）
（薬草家）　助かったわ。
Thank you.
魔法って　すごいのね。
Magic sure is amazing, isn't it?
特に銅像　サビひとつないわ。
There isn't a speck of rust left.
フフ～。
少し彩りが欲しいわね。
I wish there was a bit more color, though.
後で花でも植えようかしら。
Perhaps I'll plant some flowers later.
フリーレン様
花畑を出す魔法　使えましたよね。
Ms. Frieren, you have a spell that
produces a field of flowers, right?
そうだね　何か適当な花でも…。
You're right. I guess I could just
conjure something up...
いや　蒼月草の花がいいか。
No, blue moon weed flowers would be best.
それは　どのような花なのですか？
What kind of flowers are those?
知らない　見たことないから。
I don't know. I've never seen them.
では　なぜ…。
Then why?
ヒンメルの故郷の花だ。
They grow in Himmel's hometown.
でも　見たことない花は
魔法では…。
But you can't conjure flowers
you've never seen before.
ウフっ。
蒼月草　懐かしい名前ね。
Blue moon weed...
Now that's a name I haven't
heard in a long time.
昔は　あの森の奥にも
群生地があったんだけれどもね。
Long ago, there used to be a
field of them in those woods.
ここら辺には　もうないの？
They don't grow around here anymore?
絶滅したのよ。
They all died out.
この大陸での目撃例は
もう何十年もないわ。
It's been decades since they've
been spotted in these lands.
そう。
I see.
フェルン　行くよ。
はい。
Let's go, Fern.
Okay.
何か隠したね。
You're hiding something.
怒らないから見せなさい。
I won't be mad, so show me what it is.
シードラットだね
種を食べる害獣だよ。
They're seed rats. Pests that consume seeds.
森へ返します。
I'll release them in the woods.
じゃあ　フェルン
蒼月草を探しに行こうか。
Fern, shall we go look for blue moon weed?
本気でございますか？
Are you serious?
少し前まで
この森の奥に群生地が…。
There was a field of them
in these woods until recently.
何十年も前です。
That was decades ago.
でも　探す価値はあるよ。
But they're worth looking for.
実物を見つけて分析すれば➡
If we find and analyze them, we can acquire
a spell for conjuring blue moon weed flowers.
蒼月草の花を咲かせる
魔法が手に入る。
ヒンメル様のためですか？
For Mr. Himmel?
いや…　きっと自分のためだ。
No...
I'm probably doing this for myself.
フリーレン様
蒼月草を探し始めてから➡
Ms. Frieren, we've been searching for
blue moon weed for six months now.
もう半年になりますね。
そうだね
そろそろ探索範囲を広げようか。
You're right. Perhaps we should
broaden our search area.
（ノック）
あら　１人だなんて珍しいわね。
Oh, I don't often see you on your own.
あなたたちが村に来て
随分になるわね。
It's been a while since you
first came to the village.
蒼月草は見つかったのかしら？
Have you found any blue moon weed?
見つかると思いますか？
ん？
Do you think we'll find any?
フリーレン様の
魔法に対する執着は異常です。
Ms. Frieren's obsession with
magic is extraordinary.
このままでは　何年でも何十年でも
探し続けてしまう。
At this rate, she'll continue searching
for years, if not decades.
フリーレン様は　多くの人を
救える力を持った魔法使いです。
She's a mage who possesses the
power to save many people.
ありもしないもののために
時間を使うだなんて➡
She shouldn't spend her time searching
for something that doesn't exist.
あってはならないことです。
若いわね。
You're so young.
私の考えは
間違っているのでしょうか？
Am I wrong?
そうは思わないわ。
I don't think so,
でも　フリーレンさんにとっては
違うのでしょうね。
but Ms. Frieren must see things differently.
だけど彼女のほうが
私たちよりも　ずっと大人だから➡
But since she's so much more
mature than we are,
その気持ちを素直に伝えれば
きっと分かってくれるはずよ。
I'm sure she'd understand if you honestly
conveyed those feelings to her.
薬効があるため保管されていた➡
These are the seeds of a related species
she kept for their medicinal properties.
近縁種の種だそうです。
これを代わりにヒンメル様の
像の周りに植えるというのは…。
Could we plant these around
Himmel's statue instead?
分かったよ　フェルン。
I get it, Fern.
心配させてしまったね。
I made you worry.
私一人の時間ってわけでもない。
I'm not just spending my own time on this.
潮時だ。
It's time to go.
もう少し探したら切り上げるよ。
I'll end my search soon.
もう少しって何年ですか？
How many years is soon?
もう少しだよ。
Soon.
あなたは　本当に諦めが…。
You don't know when to stop—
シ～っ。
（種をかじる音）
あっ。
追いかけてみようか。
Shall we follow it?
フリーレン様は
なぜ魔法を集めているのですか？
Ms. Frieren, why do you collect spells?
ただの趣味だよ。
It's just a hobby of mine.
そうは思えません。
I find that hard to believe.
本当に　ただの趣味だよ。
It really is just a hobby.
前は　もっと無気力に
ダラダラと生きていたんだけどね。
I used to live much more apathetically.
｟わぁ…｠
｟アッハハハ…｠
｟フフフフ…｠
｟ハハハ…｠
｟気持ち悪い｠
Gross.
｟フッ｠
私の集めた魔法を
褒めてくれたバカがいた。
But then I got to know an idiot who
complimented the spells I gathered.
それだけだよ。
That's all.
くだらない理由ですね。
That's a silly reason.
そうだね。
You're right.
それ…。
花弁だね。
Is that...
It's a petal.
シードラットは
餌を外敵のいない➡
They say seed rats bury their food
in safe places away from enemies.
安全な場所に埋めて隠す
といわれている。
賢い動物なのですね。
They're clever animals, aren't they?
そうでもない。
I wouldn't say that.
何か所にも埋めるから
よく埋めた場所を忘れるんだ。
Since they bury their food in so many places,
they often forget where.
（アイゼン：ハイター）｟ハハハ…！｠
｟蒼月草？｠
Blue moon weed?
｟僕の故郷の花でね
とても美しいんだ｠
It's a flower that grows in
my homeland. It's beautiful.
｟まぁ　僕ほどでは
ないんだけどね｠
Not as beautiful as me, though.
｟そろそろ行こうか｠
Shall we get going?
｟フリーレン
いつか君に見せてあげたい｠
Frieren.
Someday, I'd like to show them to you.
｟そう　機会があればね｠
I see.
If we have the opportunity, perhaps.
あるとは思っていたけど
まさか　これほどとはね。
I figured they'd be here,
but I wasn't expecting so many.
遅くなったね　ヒンメル。
It took longer than I would've liked, Himmel.
本当に見つけてしまうだなんて…。
I can't believe we really found them.
これで蒼月草の魔法が作れるよ。
Now we can create a spell for blue moon weed.
何で　そんなに
魔法に一生懸命に…。
Why are you so passionate about magic?
理解できません。
I don't understand.
分かるはずだよ。
But you do.
フェルンだって魔法使いに
なることを諦めなかった。
You never gave up on becoming a mage.
それは違います。
That's different.
私は１人で生きていける力さえ
手に入れば➡
I would've been happy to learn any skill
that allowed me to support myself.
何でもよかったのです。
別に魔法じゃなくたって。
It didn't have to be magic...
でも　魔法を選んだ。
But you chose magic.
そうですね。
You're right.
（薬草家）　まさか　もう一度➡
I never thought I'd see blue moon weed again.
蒼月草が見られるなんてね。
ホントにキレイ。
They're beautiful.
フフン。
ありがとうね　フリーレンさん。
Thank you, Ms. Frieren.
これなら　きっと
この像も忘れられずに済むわ。
Now this statue will never be forgotten.
あっ　忘れるところだった。
Oh, I nearly forgot.
よし。
There.
あら　かわいらしい。
How cute.
それじゃ　行こうか。
Shall we go?
That's too powerful.
The Elder Sage of Corruption, Qual.
He called you heartless for not checking on him.
Let's put that into practice.
How many years do you think
we've traveled together?
Does this journey have a purpose?
Classroom study is important, too.
Episode 3
Killing Magic
Killing magic.